A Guide to the Madison College Student Protest, April 1970, Oral History Collection: SdArch 11
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Madison College Student Protest, April 1970, Oral History Collection, 1998
Special Collections, James Madison University
Turner, Jeremy
SdArch 11
218
.3 cubic feet; 4 folders, 5 audiocassettes, 5 cds
The Madison College Student Protest, April 1970, Oral History Collection, 1998, is comprised of audio recordings, transcripts and a background paper documenting three interviews with individuals involved with student protests that occurred at Madison College in February and April, 1970.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open to research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Jeremy Turner, May 15, 1998.
Biographical / Historical
Jeremy Turner, an undergraduate student at James Madison University, conducted these interviews in fulfillment of a JMU student internship, during the Spring of 1998.
Scope and Content
The Madison College Student Protest, April 1970, Oral History Collection, 1998, is comprised of audio recordings, transcripts and a background paper documenting three interviews with individuals involved with student protests that occurred at Madison College in February and April, 1970. Interviews are conducted with Jay Rainey, Lewis Sword, students who participated in the protests, and Dr. James Wood, a retired History professor at James Madison University.
Arrangement
Interviews are arranged chronologically.
- 11-1: Background Paper to Oral History Interviews, Jeremy Turner, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  This monograph reviews some of the factors and events surrounding academic unrest and general radicalism that were prevalent on American campuses during the 1960s and early 1970s. Mentions national campus involvment and support for the Civil Rights Movement; free speech (including the Free Speech Movement (FSM) at the U. of Cal., Berkeley); anti-Vietnam War demonstrations; and general rebellion against college administrative authority as exemplified by such groups as SDS (Students for a Democratic Society) and the concept of Free Universities. Also records general factors and specific events leading to three protests that occurred at Madison College (Harrisonburg, Va.) in February and April, 1970. Reviews general factors such as the concept of "in loco parentis," the dress code, and other rules/regulations that governed women at that time at the college. Mentions other factors leading to change, including increased enrollment of men and the gradual change of the institution from a traditional Southern teachers' womens' college to a co-educational one. Reviews specific events precipitating the protests, namely the decision by the administration and President G. Tyler Miller to deny renewal of contracts to three liberal-minded faculty members, James McClung, Houston Rodgers and Rodger Adkins. Records attempts by students Jay Rainey, Louis Sword and others (Harambee student association) to reverse the decision culminating in three protests, the final one resulting in the arrest of twenty-eight students and two professors. Mentions the trial, involvement of the ACLU, appeals, and jail sentences of three protestors which were later commuted. Interviews were conducted with two former students involved in leading the protests, Jay Rainey and Lewis Sword, and Dr. John Wood, a faculty member (now retired), who was sympathetic to their viewpoints.
- 11-2: Jay Rainey interviewed by Jeremy Turner, January 30, 1998
  Records the reminiscences of Jay Rainey, campus activist and perceived radical at Madison College during the late 1960s and early 1970s. Mentions campus life as one of the first male students at the predominantly women's teachers' college. Remembers various run-ins with the school's administration (President Dr. G. Tyler Miller, Dr. James Fox) over issues ranging from personal appearance (including winning a suit against his suspension by the college), to academic freedom, to anti-Vietnam War issues. Mentions attendance at anti-War demonstrations in Washington, D.C., and his participation and leadership in the formation of Harambee, a student activist group (Lewis Sword, etc.); Jane Fonda; also, the couple of sit-ins that occurred on the Madison College campus. In particular, mentions the student protest over the non-reappointment of three liberal-minded faculty members: James McClung, Houston Rodgers and Rodger Adkins; the consequent April 1970 sit-in at Wilson Hall on campus supporting their cause which resulted in the arrests of students and faculty; support by sympathetic faculty; his trial, jail time, and appeals. Recorded at Jay Rainey's place of work, Blacksburg, Va. on January 30, 1998
  - Transcript, January 30, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Original audiocassette #1, January 30, 1998 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA011-CS-001)
  - Original audiocassette #2, January 30, 1998 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA011-CS-003)
  - Preservation master cd #1 (Box 1, Cd SA011-OP-001)
  - Preservation master cd #2 (Box 1, Cd SA011-OP-002)
  - Use copy audiocassette #1 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA011-CS-002)
- 11-3: Lewis Sword interviewed by Jeremy Turner, February 18, 1998
  Records the reminiscences of Lewis (Lou) Sword, observer/on-the-fringes student activist at Madison College during the late 1960s and early 1970s. Mentions campus life at the predominantly women's teachers' college and various issues that were the topic of discussion and demonstrations (local issues related to the concept of "in loco parentis," various dress rules and regulations; anti-war; and the major issue of non-reappointment of three faculty. Comments on the open meetings between the school administration (President Dr. G. Tyler Miller, Dr. James Fox) and students; his viewpoints on various administrative decisions; and his participation as a writer for the student newspaper, "The Fixer," and later break-up with the group. Mentions attendance at an anti-War demonstration in Washington, D.C. In particular, relates events leading to the student protest over the non-reappointment of three liberal faculty members: James McClung, Houston Rodgers and Rodger Adkins, the consequent February march and April 1970 sit-in at Wilson Hall on campus supporting their cause and the ideal of free speech; the arrests of students and faculty; trial, jail time, and appeals. Recorded at Lewis Sword's place of work, the Harrisonburg Daily News-Record, Harrisonburg, Va. on February 18, 1998.
  - Transcript, February 18, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Original audiocassette, February 18, 1998 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA011-CS-005)
  - Preservation master cd (Box 1, Cd SA011-OP-003)
- 11-4: Dr. John Wood interviewed by Jeremy Turner, March 4, 1998
  ecords the reminiscences of Dr. John Wood, retired history professor (1960-1997) at Madison College/James Madison University, of the time period during the late 1960s and early 1970s. Mentions campus life at the predominantly women's teachers' college and various issues that were the topic of discussion and demonstrations (social issues related to the concept of "in loco parentis," various dress rules and regulations for women; anti-war; and the major issue of non-reappointment of three faculty. Comments on the friction between school administration (President Dr. G. Tyler Miller, Dr. James Fox) and towns people and students; his viewpoints on various administrative decisions; and the subject of "due process" (ex. for tenure decisions). In particular, relates events leading to the student protest over the non-reappointment of three liberal faculty members: James McClung, Houston Rodgers and Rodger Adkins, the consequent February march and April 1970 sit-in at Wilson Hall on campus supporting their cause and the ideal of free speech; the arrests of students and faculty; and his support for those arrested. Compares and contrasts Presidents Miller and Dr. Ronald Carrier. Recorded at Dr. John Wood's home, Harrisonburg, Va., on March 4, 1998.
  - Transcript, March 4, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Original audiocassette, March 4, 1998 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA011-CS-004)
  - Preservation master cd #1 (Box 1, Cd SA011-OP-004)
  - Preservation master cd #2 (Box 1, Cd SA011-OP-005)